Traffic sign recognition faces a key challenge:
Balancing accuracy with computational efficiency for embedded devices.
While modern networks achieve high accuracy, speed remains
under research.
This study asks, can the 30-year-old
LeNet-5 still compete?
Our methodology has three parts.
First, we compare four architectures on GTSRB.
Second, we fine-tune LeNet-5 to maximize performance.
Third, we conduct ablation studies to validate each
design choice.
We use GTSRB over 50,000 images across
43 imbalanced classes.
Our metrics balance prediction quality and computational efficiency.
MiniVGG leads in accuracy at 98%, but
LeNet-5 delivers exceptional speed, processing 120,000 images
per second on my personal device, which is
four times faster than MiniVGG, with only
2% accuracy loss.
This demonstrates a fundamental accuracy speed tradeoff.
Ablation studies validate LeNet-5's design.
Data augmentation showed minimal improvement because GTSRB has
already had sufficient natural variation.
Alternative kernels and activation functions dramatically degraded performance,
confirming that the original 5x5 kernels and RELU
are optimal for this shallow architecture.
Fine-tuning experiments with label smoothing and optimizer
adjustments revealed that LeNet-5 already operates near its
performance ceiling.
This validates the robustness of the original architecture.
MiniVGG's deeper architecture with sequential 3x3 blocks
creates a robust feature hierarchy for complex patterns,
but requires 8.6x more computation.
LeNet-5's shallow design with 5x5 kernels minimizes overhead
while maintaining adequate capacity, enabling four times faster
actual inference.
So, for real-time embedded systems with limited
resources, LeNet-5 is ideal.
But for safety-critical applications with available computational
resources, MiniVGG's superior accuracy justifies the cost.
Current limitations include daytime-only images and ideal
conditions.
Future work should address adverse weather, nighttime scenarios,
and real-world testing across multiple datasets.
Our conclusion is that LeNet-5 achieves 96%
accuracy at 120,000 images per second on
my personal devices, providing its continued relevance, while
MiniVGG is more accurate.
LeNet-5 is four times faster and 87%
% lower computational cost make it ideal for
embedded real-time applications.
So, the 30-year-old architecture remains remarkably
competitive.